<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://bioai-oslo.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://bioai-oslo.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-10-07T11:45:30+00:00</updated><id>https://bioai-oslo.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>The bioAI group at Simula Research Laboratory and the University of Oslo </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Validating models - How would success in NeuroAI look like?</title><link href="https://bioai-oslo.github.io/blog/2024/validating-models-in-neuroai/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Validating models - How would success in NeuroAI look like?"/><published>2024-10-05T17:10:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-05T17:10:00+00:00</updated><id>https://bioai-oslo.github.io/blog/2024/validating-models-in-neuroai</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bioai-oslo.github.io/blog/2024/validating-models-in-neuroai/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="navigating-the-future-of-neuroai---success-and-validation-in-model-development">Navigating the Future of NeuroAI - Success and Validation in Model Development</h1> <p><a href="https://www.mn.uio.no/ccse/english/about/news-and-events/events/2024/neuro-ai-workshop.html">The NeuroAI workshop</a>, held from September 5-8, 2024, aboard the Hurtigruten cruise ship traveling from Tromsø to Trondheim, brought together leading researchers in neuroscience and artificial intelligence (AI). The picturesque Norwegian coastline provided an inspiring backdrop for an event focused on a pressing question in this emerging field: how can we validate AI models that seek to replicate or be inspired by neural processes?</p> <h2 id="the-challenge-of-validation-in-neuroai">The Challenge of Validation in NeuroAI</h2> <p>The workshop, organized by Mikkel Lepperød (Simula Research Laboratory), Anders Malthe-Sørenssen (Center for Computing in Science Education (CCSE) University of Oslo), and Konrad Kording (University of Pennsylvania), explored the intersection of neuroscience and AI, aiming to bridge gaps between model development and experimental neuroscience. Attendees delved into the complexities of creating models that not only emulate the brain’s functions but also capture its fundamental principles. The challenge of validation is significant as current models don’t correspond one-to-one with the brain but rather aim to capture some essence, such as similar representations or comparable behavior.</p> <p>The critical question remains: how can we validate these AI models as accurate representations of neural processes? How would we know that a model is good?</p> <p>The workshop featured keynote presentations from renowned scientists from around the world, and discussions addressed the philosophical and technical aspects of model validation. Sessions focused on neuronal representation, computational approaches to learning, and the overlap between AI and neural data. An overarching goal was fostering collaboration between AI modelers and experimental neuroscientists to create a symbiotic relationship where insights from one field directly inform advances in the other. Defining Success in NeuroAI</p> <p>One of the central discussions revolved around defining what “success” looks like in NeuroAI. Success, participants agreed, is multi-faceted, requiring a balance between performance metrics, biological plausibility, and cognitive alignment.</p> <p>As Justin Wood summarized: “Success will be when we can raise newborn animals and embodied models in the same environments, test them with the same tasks, and find that they both develop the same mental skills and behaviors”.</p> <p>In his reflections on the workshop, professor Gaute Einevoll noted that success would mean developing “a set of models that are mutually consistent, can explain both neurophysiological data and cognitive/behavioral data, and that account for results from causal stimulation experiments.”</p> <p>This echoed a broader consensus at the workshop: success in NeuroAI should not be measured purely by output but also by how closely models mirror biological processes. The challenge, of course, is in balancing the creation of useful AI systems with ensuring these systems remain true to the complexities of biological intelligence. Konrad Kording humorously captured the difficulty of defining success, saying, “Well, I thought I knew it. And I rated my confidence in what success would look like to 8 during the meeting. And then took it back to 5. And now it is at 4 (really convincing points people made).”</p> <h2 id="key-themes-causal-understanding-and-representation">Key Themes: Causal Understanding and Representation</h2> <p>A recurring theme at the workshop was the necessity for AI models to move beyond statistical correlation and towards causal understanding—a key element if AI is to truly replicate human intelligence. Stefano Nichele shared his vision of success as creating “AI systems that are more intelligent than current statistical and correlation-based models,” which would involve causal reasoning and understanding.</p> <p>The importance of representation was another hot topic, particularly in the context of how AI systems, like large language models, can be used to understand neural processes. Several talks discussed how representational geometry in both artificial neural networks and biological systems could be aligned to validate models. The integration of these models with neuroimaging data, such as fMRI or MEG, was highlighted as a promising way forward.</p> <h2 id="participant-feedback-and-future-directions">Participant Feedback and Future Directions</h2> <p>The workshop format encouraged both formal presentations and informal discussions, which participants found incredibly valuable. Many noted the unique nature of the event, with one attendee calling it “one of the most intellectually stimulating events I’ve been at”. The immersive environment fostered deep engagement, leading to the suggestion that future workshops could benefit from even more group discussions and longer formats.</p> <p>Looking ahead, participants expressed a strong desire for more interdisciplinary collaboration. A key takeaway was the need to integrate experimental results and causality into NeuroAI research. Future workshops were suggested to focus on refining common metrics for success and placing more emphasis on the behavioral and evolutionary aspects of intelligence.</p> <h2 id="conclusion-paving-the-way-for-neuroais-future">Conclusion: Paving the Way for NeuroAI’s Future</h2> <p>The 2024 NeuroAI workshop was a significant step in defining how the field can move forward. As the boundaries between AI and neuroscience continue to blur, the need for validated models that reflect both computational and biological realities will only grow. The challenge remains immense, but with continued collaboration and an interdisciplinary approach, NeuroAI holds the potential to revolutionize both AI development and our understanding of the brain.</p> <p>The NeuroAI workshop aboard the Hurtigruten was a unique and fruitful endeavor, bringing together some of the brightest minds to explore uncharted territories in neuroscience and AI. As the ship sailed from Tromsø to Trondheim, it carried with it not just the participants, but the seeds of future breakthroughs in understanding the brain—and how AI might one day replicate its remarkable capabilities.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="links"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Navigating the Future of NeuroAI - Success and Validation in Model Development]]></summary></entry></feed>